{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "In the nineteenth century, this country experienced the Liberal Triennium. An attempt to\nenforce the Salic Law in this country sparked the first Carlist War. This country lost nearly all of\nits overseas colonies during the early nineteenth century following the rise of Jose de San Martin\nand Miguel Hidalgo. For 10 points, name this onetime master of much of Latin America.",
      "answer": "Spain"
    },
    {
      "question": "The major theoretical advance of these people was recalculating the Smeaton coefficient to\ncorrect errors made by Otto Lilienthal. These rivals of Samuel Langley worked as publishers of\nThe West Side News and as bicycle salesmen before their breakthrough at Kill Devil Hills. For 10\npoints, identify this pair of Ohio brothers who made the first airplane flight in 1903.",
      "answer": [
        "Wright Brothers",
        "Wilbur and Orville Wright",
        "Wright"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "During this battle, Strong Vincent was killed at a site where the downhill bayonet charge led\nby Joshua Chamberlain occurred. This battle, which included the skirmish of Little Round Top,\nturned on an ill-advised \"charge\" ordered by Confederate general George Pickett. For 10 points,\nname this July 1863 clash in Pennsylvania which was the turning point of the Civil War.",
      "answer": [
        "Battle of Gettysburg",
        "Gettysburg"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This field of research was what John McCarthy was working on when he invented the LISP\nprogramming language in 1959. This field of research is the subject of John Searle's \"Chinese\nRoom\" argument and is divided into \"weak\" and \"strong\" branches. For 10 points, name this\nfield which seeks to duplicate functions of the human brain on computers.",
      "answer": [
        "artificial intelligence",
        "AI"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A 2006 contest resulted in two of these animals being given the politically explosive name\n\"reunion.\" In August 2014, one of these animals was given a first birthday party by the U.S.\nNational Zoo, and another one of these animals, Ai Hin, was caught faking a pregnancy to earn\nmore bamboo. For 10 points, name these endangered Chinese bears.",
      "answer": [
        "giant pandas",
        "panda",
        "pandas",
        "giant panda"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man once sold cards displaying Lon Horiuchi's home address at gun shows. This man\nwas inspired by reading about a fictional race war in The Turner Diaries and by the incident at\nthe Branch Davidian compound in Waco. For 10 points, name this conspirator, with Terry\nNichols, who was executed for his role in the 1995 bombing of the Murrah building in Oklahoma\nCity.",
      "answer": [
        "Timothy McVeigh",
        "McVeigh"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Karl Jaspers (pr. YOS-perz) is often called a Christian philosopher within this framework.\nThis philosophy was dubbed \"a humanism\" in a book by one of its major exponents, who also\nwrote Roads to Freedom. For 10 points, identify this philosophy originated by Soren\nKierkegaard and popularized by Jean-Paul Sartre (pr. SART) in which humans must create\nmeaning in the universe.",
      "answer": [
        "existentialism",
        "existential"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This actor played a Mexican revolutionary in Viva Zapata! and Mark Antony in the 1953\nJulius Caesar. He utters the last words \"the horror…the horror\" in his role as Kurtz in\nApocalypse Now. This star of The Wild One sent American Indian activist Sacheen Littlefeather\nto accept his Oscar for another role. For 10 points, name this portrayer of Vito Corleone in The\nGodfather.",
      "answer": [
        "Marlon Brando",
        "Brando"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A song of this kind derives its melody from \"La Montovana,\" the same folk song that is the\norigin of \"The Moldau\" (pr. MOLE-dow), and is called \"Hatikvah\" (pr. hah-TEEK-vuh).\nSongs of the kind include Jana Gana Mana (pr. jah-NAH guh-nuh MOO-nuh) and La\nMarseillaise (pr. MAHR-see-YEZ). For 10 points, identify this type of song, such as \"God Save\nthe Queen.\"",
      "answer": [
        "national anthems",
        "national anthem"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man's visit to the Keeling Islands inspired his book The Structure and Distribution of\nCoral Reefs. As part of that same trip with Robert FitzRoy, he noticed that different finches on\nthe Galapagos Islands occupied different niches. For 10 points, name this man whose time on the\nBeagle inspired him to introduce the theory of evolution by natural selection.",
      "answer": [
        "Charles Darwin",
        "Darwin"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Eddie Collins achieved this stat six times in a game on two separate occasions in September\n1912. In 1962, Maury Wills became the first modern player to achieve this feat a hundred times\nin a season, and Lou Brock once broke Ty Cobb’s record for this statistic. For 10 points, name\nthis baseball achievement whose records are now held by speedster Rickey Henderson.",
        "answer": [
          "stolen bases",
          "stolen base",
          "steals",
          "steal"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Henderson achieved the single-season and career stolen base records while playing for\nwhat team, which won the 1989 \"Earthquake Series\" against its cross-bay rivals?",
        "answer": [
          "Oakland Athletics",
          "Oakland",
          "Athletics",
          "A's"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man's victory at the 1040 battle of Elgin allowed him to become King of Alba, displacing\nDuncan I. In a fictionalized portrayal, this man is killed in battle with an opponent who, having\nbeen delivered by Caesarean section, fulfills the prophecy that \"no man of woman born\" can kill\nhim. For 10 points, name this King of Scotland killed by Macduff in a Shakespeare play.",
        "answer": "Macbeth"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In what other Shakespeare play based on history does a queen of Egypt kill herself with\nan asp following the two title characters' loss at the Battle of Actium?",
        "answer": "Antony and Cleopatra"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man's co-conspirators included Mary Surratt, who became the first woman executed by\nthe U.S. government as a result, and the doctor Samuel Mudd. This man's brother Edwin once\nsaved Robert Lincoln from being crushed by a train. This man interrupted a performance of Our\nAmerican Cousin to shout \"Sic semper tyrannis!\" For 10 points, name this disgruntled\nConfederate actor who assassinated Abraham Lincoln.",
        "answer": [
          "John Wilkes Booth",
          "Booth"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Chronologically, the next American president to be assassinated after Lincoln was\nwhich man?",
        "answer": [
          "James Garfield",
          "Garfield"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The U.S. National Archives currently displays David Rubenstein’s copy of this document,\nwhich contains clauses that limited the right of women to use the legal system and limited the\nenforcement of debts against children. This document was signed at Runnymede and failed to\nquell the Barons Wars. For 10 points, name this limitation of the powers of King John.",
        "answer": "Magna Carta"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Second Barons War ended under the rule of what king, whose army was defeated\nby William Wallace at Stirling Bridge?",
        "answer": [
          "Edward I",
          "Edward Longshanks",
          "Longshanks"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This empire was targeted by the Unilateral Declaration of Independence, which removed a\ncolony from this empire to protest its plans for racial integration. This empire's leader gave the\nWinds of Change speech as it began to give up control of Ghana, Nigeria, and Rhodesia. For 10\npoints, name this empire which, along with France, was the largest colonizer of Africa.",
        "answer": [
          "British Empire",
          "British",
          "UK",
          "United Kingdom",
          "Great Britain",
          "Britain"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Rhodesia later was renamed as which African country with its capital at the city of\nHarare (pr. huh-RAH-ray)?",
        "answer": "Zimbabwe"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "his man's lavish spending on Italian art greatly expanded the Royal Collection. This man is\ndepicted with a stable boy, a horse, a walking stick, and red trousers, looking away from the\nThames (pr. TEMZ), in a portrait of him \"at the hunt.\" For 10 points, name this king whom\nAnthony van Dyck repeatedly painted prior to his execution in the English Civil War.",
        "answer": [
          "Charles I of England",
          "Charles I"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What other court painter made an insultingly realistic portrait of Charles IV of Spain\nand his family, as well as The Third of May, 1808?",
        "answer": [
          "Francisco Goya",
          "Francisco Jose de Goya y Lucientes",
          "Goya"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This empire was attacked by Croesus (pr. CREE-sus) of Lydia after the Delphic Oracle said\nthat \"a great empire will fall.\" This empire relied on local satraps who were loyal to emperors\nsitting at Susa. For 10 points, name this empire founded by Cyrus the Great, which launched a\nnamesake series of wars on Greece at the start of the fifth century BC.",
        "answer": [
          "Persian Empire",
          "Persia",
          "Achaemenid Empire",
          "Achaemenid"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Which Persian Emperor lost at Issus and Gaugamela, and was the third to hold this\nname?",
        "answer": "Darius"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man was giving a speech that contained the line \"Caesar had his Brutus, Charles the First\nhis Cromwell\" when he was interrupted with shouts of \"Treason!\" Later, this advocate of\nresisting the Stamp Act said \"I know not what course others may take.\" For 10 points, name this\nVirginia orator who ended that speech with \"give me liberty or give me death.\"",
        "answer": [
          "Patrick Henry",
          "Henry"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Henry's Treason Speech was given to what Virginia body, the oldest legislature in the\ncolonies?",
        "answer": "House of Burgesses"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "(TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) This man was able to return to his hometown following negotiations with the tribe of the Quraish\n(pr. koo-RYE-eesh) at the Treaty of Hudaybiyyah (pr. hoo-dah-BEE-ah). This man was buried\nnext to an empty tomb which is reserved for the returned Jesus after he died in the home of his\nwife Aisha (pr. eye-EE-shuh). For ten points, name this man who received a \"recitation\" from\nthe angel Jibril (pr. jib-REEL) which became the Quran, and was the founder of Islam.",
        "answer": "Muhammad"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What largest island in the North Atlantic had its capital officially renamed from\nGodthab to Nuuk (pr. noo-ook)?",
        "answer": "Greenland"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "SOMALIA",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Colonized by what European power, but handed over to Britain following the fall of\nMussolini?",
          "answer": [
            "Kingdom of Italy",
            "Italy"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Often described as suffering from what status, meaning the lack of government, since 1991?",
          "answer": "anarchy"
        },
        {
          "question": "The source of many refugees who were resettled in which state’s capital of St. Paul?",
          "answer": "Minnesota"
        },
        {
          "question": "Home to a “courts union” and Al-Shabbab (pr. shuh-BOB), which seek to impose what\nreligion?",
          "answer": [
            "Sunni Islam",
            "Islam",
            "Muslims",
            "Muslim"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The setting for what 2001 Ridley Scott film about the 1993 events?",
          "answer": "Black Hawk Down"
        },
        {
          "question": "A frequent base for what kind of international outlaws, who also plague the Strait of Malacca\n(mah-LAH-kuh)?",
          "answer": [
            "pirates",
            "pirate",
            "piracy"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Home to what capital city, where a 1993 U.S. Army mission went awry?",
          "answer": "Mogadishu"
        },
        {
          "question": "Functionally politically separate from what northern region, which maintains an unrecognized\nindependent government at Hargeisa (pr. har-GAY-suh)?",
          "answer": "Somaliland"
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "The present-day country of Somalia is or was..."
    },
    {
      "category": "CRUSADES",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Religion whose Crusaders sought to capture Jerusalem from Muslim Turks?",
          "answer": [
            "Christianity",
            "Christian",
            "Roman Catholicism",
            "Catholic",
            "Catholicism"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Religious group which was the target of pogroms in the Rhineland at the hands of the People's\nCrusade?",
          "answer": "Jews"
        },
        {
          "question": "King of England who left his brother John in charge while he led the Third Crusade?",
          "answer": [
            "Richard the Lionheart",
            "Richard I",
            "Richard Coeur de Lion"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Kurdish founder of the Ayyubid (pr. eye-OO-bid) Dynasty who was the opponent of the\nThird Crusade?",
          "answer": [
            "Saladin",
            "Salah al-Din"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Sea across which Crusaders sailed to the Holy Land?",
          "answer": [
            "Mediterranean Sea",
            "Mediterranean"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Type of defensive building, such as Krak des Chevaliers (pr. KRAG doo shoo-vahl-YAY),\noften constructed by Crusaders?",
          "answer": [
            "castles",
            "castle"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Pope who called for the First Crusade?",
          "answer": "Urban II"
        },
        {
          "question": "Crusade which descended into looting and sacked Constantinople?",
          "answer": [
            "Fourth Crusade",
            "Fourth"
          ]
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "In the era of the Crusades, who or what was the..."
    },
    {
      "category": "ANCIENT INDIA",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Nirvana-focused religion founded by Siddhartha Gautama?",
          "answer": [
            "Buddhism",
            "Buddhist"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Language ancestral to modern Hindi that was used to write ancient Hindu texts?",
          "answer": "Sanskrit"
        },
        {
          "question": "Number first articulated in fifth-century India during the invention of decimals?",
          "answer": [
            "zero",
            "shunya"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "River at which Indian civilization grew near the city of Varanasi?",
          "answer": "Ganges"
        },
        {
          "question": "Macedonian general who reached the borders of India with his conquests?",
          "answer": [
            "Alexander the Great",
            "Alexander"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Treatise on the art of love composed around the second century AD?",
          "answer": [
            "Kama Sutra",
            "Kamasutra"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Epic about the king of Ayodha (pr. eye-OH-duh) defeating the demon Ravana?",
          "answer": "the Ramayana"
        },
        {
          "question": "Dynasty in power from 322 to 185 BC, whose emperors included Asoka (pr. uh-SHOWkuh)?",
          "answer": [
            "Mauryan dynasty",
            "Maurya",
            "Mauryan empire"
          ]
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "In classical India, what was the..."
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Theodor Adorno said that after the existence of this place, writing poetry is barbaric.\nThis place was built near a massive, forty-four track (20 pts) ",
        "railway junction and was\ncommanded by Rudolph Hoss. At the main gate of this place, the words \"Arbeit Macht\nFrei\" (pr. ARR-bite mokt FRY), meaning (10 pts) ",
        "\"work makes free,\" were spelled out in iron. It\nwas adjacent to the Birkenau extermination center. For 10 points, name this most active Nazi\ndeath camp, found in Poland."
      ],
      "answer": "Auschwitz"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) These people were the target of 1913's Alien Land Law. These people were guaranteed\nequal access to public schools as part of the (20 pts) ",
        "\"Gentlemen's Agreement\" which restricted\ntheir further immigration. They were later relocated to facilities such as Manzanar as part\nof a practice upheld by the (10 pts) ",
        "Supreme Court in the Korematsu case. For 10 points, name this\ngroup which was subject to World War II \"internment\" on the West Coast."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Japanese-Americans",
        "Japanese"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In the third century AD, this building was the home of a red idol with a golden right\nhand that depicted Hubal. The construction of this building was traditionally attributed to (20 pts) ",
        "Ibrahim, who journeyed with his son Ishmael to a spot near the Well of Zamzam. This\nbuilding was cleared of idols near the start of the (10 pts) ",
        "Islamic era and is now the destination of\nthe hajj, or pilgrimage. For 10 points, name this black, square building around which Mecca is\nbuilt."
      ],
      "answer": "the Kaaba"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A U.S. State Department memo on this initiative said that it was \"a flying saucer—\nnobody knows what it looks like, how big it is, in what direction it is moving, or whether it\nreally exists.\" Ultimately, this program transferred (20 pts) ",
        "seventeen billion dollars in cash and\ngoods, and hardened (10 pts) ",
        "Cold War divisions as Soviet client states were forbidden to\nparticipate. For 10 points, name this 1947 initiative under which American money was pumped\ninto Western European economies."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Marshall Plan",
        "Marshall"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This program was upheld as Constitutional by the Supreme Court in the cases of\nSteward Machine Company v. Davis and Helvering v. Davis. This program was inspired by\nthe \"revolving\" plan advocated by Francis (20 pts) ",
        "Townsend, and it issued its first card to Ida\nMay Fuller. The first, two billion dollar wave of (10 pts) ",
        "taxes collected to fund this program may\nhave triggered the 1937 recession. For 10 points, name this retiree pension program in the United\nStates."
      ],
      "answer": "Social Security"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 1988, the U.S.S. Vincennes accidentally shot down a passenger plane from this\ncountry. Kermit Roosevelt led a CIA action against the prime minister of this country,\nOperation (20 pts) ",
        "Ajax, which deposed Mohammad Mossadiq. Jimmy Carter's decision to\nallow the deposed ruler of this country to seek medical treatment in the U.S. in (10 pts) ",
        "1979\nsparked an incident here. For 10 points, name this country which took fifty-two Americans\nhostage for over a year."
      ],
      "answer": "Iran"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) An event which began on this ship provided the nickname for Molly Brown. Frederick\nFleet was unable to avert disaster aboard this ship despite performing adequate lookout\nduties, and many of its (20 pts) ",
        "survivors were picked up by the Carpathia. Edward J. Smith\ncaptained this ship on behalf of the (10 pts) ",
        "White Star Line. For 10 points, name this ship whose\nattempt to make good time to New York caused it to hit an iceberg and sink in the north Atlantic\nin April 1912."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "RMS Titanic",
        "Titanic"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In an 1890 treaty, this empire abandoned its interest in Zanzibar in exchange for an\noddly shaped territory that granted it access to the Zambezi River, known as the Caprivi\nStrip. This empire perpetrated the Herero genocide in what is now (20 pts) ",
        "Namibia. It had to\ngive up what are now Tanzania and Cameroon following its defeat in (10 pts) ",
        "World War I. For\n10 points, name this European-based empire, which was originally constructed by Otto von\nBismarck."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "German Empire",
        "German"
      ]
    }
  ]
}